if you don't want a man unhappy don't
give him two sides of a question to
worry about give him one better yet give
him
none dystopias and apocalypses are never
too far from the collective imagination
of a society from ancient Rome to
Victorian Britain there are always
writers anxiously warning about the ways
they think the world could come crashing
down sometimes the collapse comes from a
perceived loss of moral fiber sometimes
it comes from a superior f or a
dictatorial political party but in Ray
Bradbury's Fahrenheit 451 it comes from
the state's terrifying and total control
of information books and unapproved
ideas wherever they are found are burnt
to ashes by agents of the government
even more frightening this happens with
the near tootal consent and support of
the general populace in a world where
how we handle disseminate and process
information is changing at an alarming
pace
I think it's worth looking back at this
20th century classic to see what it can
teach us about our own world and where
our own societies may go dangerously
wrong but let's start with a brief bit
of background to the novel and its world
before exploring what makes Fahrenheit
451 so terrifying and remarkably
prophetic be warned spoilers lie ahead
one Fahrenheit
451 a brief synopsis
Fahrenheit 451 is not a particularly
long novel and yet it crams quite a lot
in so I'll start by explaining the
general setting of the world and then go
through the important plot points just
so we're all up to speed going into the
analysis the setting of Fahrenheit 451
is the United States of America at some
point in the indeterminate future the
most famous feature of this dystopia is
that almost all books have been banned
technology has accelerated to such an
extent that people have lost interest in
book books altogether and the state
considers them dangerous as a result
anyone caught in possession of a book is
arrested and their house is burnt To The
Ground by the firemen these firemen are
a twisted development of the
firefighters of today they no longer put
fires out but intentionally start them
to destroy as many books as possible as
far as the government is concerned books
are full of confusing ideas that will
only harm the general populace and the
people of America America consume
preapproved media relate to them through
immersive television systems the story
follows just one of these firan guy
Montag as he gradually becomes
disillusioned with both his job and the
society his fires uphot this begins when
he meets a young woman named Clarice who
strikes up a conversation with him on
his walk home from work Clarice is from
a strange family who just do not behave
like everyone else they still talk
debate discuss and do not engage with
the new technological advances that
others adore so much at the same time
montag's wife Mildred attempts to end
her own life yet refuses to talk about
it or even acknowledge that it's
happened it's almost like she does not
know how to put her dissatisfaction into
words Montag then interrogates his life
is he really content or is he just numb
the final nail in the coffin for him is
when he and his fellow firemen burn down
a house on their next ship rather than
be arrested or flee the woman who owns
the house and the books within refuses
to leave choosing to perish with her
books rather than betray her principles
Montag begins to steal books from the
houses the fireman burn down and he
keeps them in his own home at this point
it is also revealed that Clarice has
died in a car accident under slightly
mysterious circumstances and her family
has moved away in response to all this
Montag calls in sick for work the next
day but his captain Bey shows up at the
house to check in on him Bey delivers a
long speech about how books came to be
banned and how the firemen came to burn
them he heavily insinuates that he knows
Montag has been stealing books and that
Montag has only a limited time to turn
back from this path before dire
consequences will be visited both upon
him and his family monag is unswayed by
be's threats and he setss out to meet a
man he suspected of harboring old books
but who he never reported to the
authorities for reasons he just can't
quite put his finger on this man Faber
was an English professor before all of
the universities were shut down together
they hatch plans to plant books in the
homes of firemen all across the nation
and to start a printing press plans that
unfortunately will never come to
fruition the next day Mildred has two
friends over who are discussing the
impending war that it looks like America
will become involved in they have a
callous attitude seeming not
understanding that human lives are going
to be lost and hearing this Montag has a
breakdown he recites poetry at them and
berates them for their shallow
acceptance of society as it exists which
then causes them to run out of the house
inevitably raising suspicions about
Montag in order to maintain his cover
and to throw Bey off the scent Montag
hands over one of the books he hoarded
and it is burnt he and BT then have a
verbal sparring match about the very
nature of literature which I will go
into far more detail about later in the
video BT maintains that the populace
having access to books is too dangerous
the ideas are too distressing and if
people are allowed to have different
ideas this is the first step to conflict
cutting the conversation short BT says
they must head out to burn down another
house where someone has been collecting
books he then drives Montag to his own
house and instructs him to burn it down
with a flamethrower we see Mildred
leaving the home refusing to to engage
with her now criminal husband Montag
carries out this maab order before
finally turning the weapon on B
wondering if that is what B wanted all
along Montag is now on the run after an
extended Chase he manages to lose the
police and finds himself in the American
Countryside he remembers hearing some
rumors that there were people on the Run
who traveled the old railway tracks
guarding books and agitating for change
so he heads to the nearest line after
some walking he meets a group of these
literary fugitives led by a man called
Granger Granger reveals that they do not
keep physical books as this is too
dangerous books can be burnt after all
instead they memorize entire volumes of
text spreading out a vast libraries
worth of wisdom between them they hope
that one day when the time is right they
can reconvene and put these books back
on paper at this very moment the war
that we briefly mentioned earlier begins
with nuclear Devastation raining down on
the city that Montag has just fled it
ends almost as soon as it starts and
civilization as everyone knew it
flickers and dies like a candle it is
unclear what the road ahead looks like
for Montag but he and the other
fugitives hope to contribute to the
rebuilding of this world in a better way
so that when the dust settles there is
knowledge wisdom and thought where
previously there was simply noise
Fahrenheit 451 has a very compelling
narrative there is a reason it's one of
the bestselling novels of the past 70
years and I think that Bradbury's world
is actually a lot more complex and
Nuance than people tend to give him
credit for so let's start with perhaps
the most prominent theme in the book and
the first thing that leaps out to most
people on a first read the extreme
censorship of Bradbury's state if you
want to help me make more vide like this
then please consider subscribing to my
patreon or my substack to help the
channel the links are in the description
two the philosophy of censorship 20th
century dystopian fiction almost seems
dominated by themes of censorship and
surveillance in 1984 Winston Smith is
kept under near constant monitoring by
the party in power who concart him away
to be tortured and executed at any
moment if he commits a thought crime in
huxley's Brave New World the ideas that
can be expressed are limited by strict
cultural tabos and literal mind control
and any who did manage to break them
were shipped off into Exile but despite
surface level similarities each of these
dystopias treats censorship in
importantly different ways in 1984 it is
enforced by the terrifying secret police
in Brave New World most people just
don't think to express dissenting ideas
because of the psychological control
mechanisms that attack their very will
but in Fahrenheit 4 51 we see some ways
that censorship is motivated and carried
out that is importantly different from
these other worlds and I think this is
worth examining the main mouthpiece we
have for the philosophy of the state in
Fahrenheit 451 is Bey the captain of
montag's fire department according to
him the trouble with books and the ideas
that they contain is twofold they
encourage dangerous independent thought
and they are in themselves worthless
according to be's philosophy y deeper
ideas engender substantive disagreements
between people and these disagreements
will spill over into conflict or harm
they thus fly in the face of what he
thinks a healthy Society really needs
Unity an almost fetishistic exaltation
of unity and similarity pervades the
world of Fahrenheit 451 it is to the
point where the simple Act of going for
a walk late at night is seen as
suspicious and a cause for the fire
department to investigate your home BT
justifies this with what is commonly
known as the harm argument for
censorship this is a pretty
straightforward idea people justify
sensorship on the grounds that the free
expression of ideas will cause harm and
BT is probably right that in the short
term the effect of millions of people
suddenly being exposed to thousands of
new ideas probably will cause conflict
there'll be disputes over policy
politics and social organization there
will be arguments and maybe even fights
over the value of of art what is worth
paying attention to and how we should
treat our fellow man people will care
about things and with that care will
inevitably come some conflict after all
as Renee Gerard once pointed out
conflict often occurs when two people
care about the same thing to different
ends but the dangerous assumption BT
makes is that the status quo is
inherently better than the temporary
conflict that might arise if people were
exposed to new ideas it is quite similar
to the point Thomas Hobbs made in his
Landmark work Leviathan Hobbs wrote this
book in the midst of the English Civil
War and runs through the essays is a
total distrust in the ability of people
to resolve conflicts amicably as he put
it competition of riches honor command
or other power inclin to contention
enmity and War because the way of one
competitor to the attaining of his
desire is to kill subdue supplant or
repel the other in other words where
there is difference and competition in
AIM there is violence Hobs thus
recommended that we place our trust in a
single Sovereign who would wield almost
absolute power while Hobbs does give
positive Arguments for why he thinks
this would be desirable Leviathan also
has a strong sense of the alternative is
far worse about it for Hobs people in
groups are simply not well equipped to
share power or to participate in
government submission to a wise a higher
authority is then the sensible course of
action BT's perspective makes sense if
we consider him an extreme hsian someone
primarily concerned with preventing
Society from falling into chaos at any
cost this also explains why he views
works like poetry novels ethical
philosophy free art reflection and
discussion as fundamentally useless in
what way would the proliferation of
these viewpoints bolster the strength
and stability of the St probably not at
all for him it is much safer to allow a
narrow set of views among the general
populace besides as he repeatedly States
it will only distress the people when
their new theories cause them to have
those Oho upsetting
disagreements of course there is a
reason why most people get the feeling
that BT's analysis of the world is
missing something and they would not be
alone even thinkers who have emphasized
Notions of Duty and obligation like Leo
Strauss accuse The hsian View on
Politics as having an unduly pessimistic
standpoint on human nature someone like
BT reduces down the questions of
politics and social organization into
just a matter of preventing collapse
this fear-based framework heavily
implies a kind of blunt authoritarianism
Hannah arent went one step further and
criticized this Hobs and view as leading
to Everyday people seeing themselves as
completely divorced from the running of
their own Society tricked into thinking
they are purely private entities who are
only able to pursue narrow selfish aims
like the accumulation of power in both
cases Hobs is charged with an overly
restrictive view of humanity which
paints us all as borderline incapable of
empathy fellow feeling Higher Goals or
virtue be's philosophy similarly reduces
Humanity down to Simply seeking
short-term pleasure and pain why bother
with ideas when we can remain perfectly
entertained without them why bother with
reflection when it could bring painful
self-examination why think about values
or creativity or discussion when there
is no immediate benefit to be had in
terms of personal pleasure and it may
threaten the very social order we live
in with a dissenting idea this is a very
different kind of totalitarian reasoning
from the party in 1984 they explicitly
desire power for its own sake and say
they serve no higher mistress than this
but Bey turns this accusation around on
us for him we are all power seeking and
hungry for conflict it is the duty of he
and his fellow firemen to ensure that we
never get our hands on any ideas which
might encourage our inherently dangerous
nature it's another thing that sets
Fahrenheit 451 apart from a lot of other
dystopias normally the people are afraid
of the state but here the state is just
as afraid of its people of course the
irony is that from what little we see of
The Wider world of Fahrenheit 451 it is
actually a very violent place in some of
clarice's early interactions with Montag
she says that people her age have turned
incredibly violent even killing one
another in some cases Monte himself is
almost run over by a vindictive gang of
young men when he's fleeing from the
police so on reflection it is not quite
right to say that the state of
Fahrenheit 451 desires nonviolence or
peace while the justification BT gives
for the oppressive regime is that the
state guarantees peace and stability it
is more accurate to say that the state
considers the situation peaceful so long
as it is not threatened there can be
substantial violence within its borders
so long as that does not compromise the
proper functioning of the government at
some point the strength and authority of
the state ceased to be a means to
stability and became an end in itself
and if the strength of the state is an
inherently good thing then why not Crush
any dissenting ideas any potential for
independent thought why not censor
whatever you please thinking itself
becomes a new kind of blasphemy and all
the churches turn to the halls of
governance but despite being the most
dramatic aspect of the state's power in
Fahrenheit 451 censorship is only a
minor part of its strategy perhaps even
more important is the information
campaign they wage on the minds of their
citizens three amusing ourselves to
death in 1985 the American cultural
critic Neil Postman published an essay
called amusing ourselves to death where
he takes aim at the effect of television
on public discourse according to postman
the trouble with television is that it
is incredibly Adept at holding our
attention merely through entertainment
value it is not that complex ideas could
never be discussed on television but the
particular strengths of that Medium
means they will normally be outcompeted
by flashier more engaging shows just as
the written word is exceptionally
effective at communicating ideas but it
is much more fun to watch a play than
simply read a script a television is
better adapted to entertainment than to
deep reflection according to postman it
plays to the television's inherent
strengths Postman Compares this value
placed on what he sees as numb
entertainment to s from huxley's Brave
New World there Soma is a medicine which
dulls someone's sense of sadness and
thus causes them to be happy for a short
time however I think that the world of
Fahrenheit 451 forms a slightly better
comparison because whereas Soma is
distraction by medication Fahrenheit 451
focuses on distraction by media and the
thing about distraction by media is that
it is fundamentally distraction by
information that is it occupies our
attention by filling our minds with
content that does not enrich us
challenge us or teach us but simply
appeals to our senses and our short-term
emotions it is not that there is
anything inherently wrong with this
entertainment can be great but in
Fahrenheit 451 entertainment has
entirely replaced thought with
unsurprisingly pretty drastic
consequences the character who most
embodies this is Mildred montag's wife
she spends almost all of her time in her
parlor this is a sort of whole room
television with interactive characters
who actually respond to her voice she
develops such an attachment to them that
she calls them her family even though
we're given no reason to believe that
they're conscious this is how she fills
her days she watches shows on the Parlor
occasionally interacting with them and
then she discusses those shows with her
friends she becomes almost addicted to
this to the point where even when Montag
says he is ill and is clearly in need of
her help she can barely tear s away from
these screens if in 1984 the tellor
screen watched you in Fahrenheit 451
we're all transfix to the telescreen and
it is staggering the effect this has on
Mildred she is almost completely unable
to empathize with the people around her
or form particularly deep relationships
the same goes for her friends one of
them talks about how her husband will
likely be drafted in the upcoming War
but that she doesn't really mind very
much after all it's his life if he dies
she will simply find someone else for
Mildred and her friends The Parlor and
their Virtual Families fulfill whatever
urge for human connection they might
have or I should say they almost do
because even in the short time we see
them it becomes clear that Mildred's
friends have a profound emptiness inside
for a start at only the slightest
provocation from Montag one of them
almost has a complete meltdown sobbing
uncontrollably when he recites poetry
they seem to be vaguely aware that their
shallow satisfaction does mask an
underlying lack but they avoid this
realization like the plague as kard
might put it they are at the deepest
point in despair so deep that they are
not even aware of its existence their
despair just forms the backdrop of their
world as water does to a fish arguably
the most extreme suffering is seen in
Mildred herself who attempts to end her
own life in one of the very first scenes
of the novel and when a medical team
comes to resuscitate her they casually
remark that they get N9 or 10 cases just
like this a night the kind of human
connection that would fulfill Mildred or
her friends simply cannot be found in
the virtual plane it requires embodied
engagement with another conscious
agential person they do not need to be
entertained they need to connect they
could each stand in a room full of
people and yet be fundamentally alone I
don't even need to finish the analogy to
show how this Insight might be
applicable today different philosophers
might put this in different ways kamu
might say they are deprived of the
shared solidarity needed to face life's
emptiness Axel honth might say that they
lack Mutual recognition whatever it is
it is slowly dooming the people of
Fahrenheit 451 to misery and again we
see the flawed logic of Bey even if
conflict were minimized it would come at
the cost of an inner void that is just
as threatening the whole of human
existence reduced to meaningless
entertainment as Montag puts it if she
died he was certain he wouldn't cry for
it would be the dying of an unknown a
silly empty man near a silly empty woman
but the worst part of all is that the
people asked for this according to Bey
the ban on books and on the
proliferation of ideas more generally
was not imposed from above against the
resistance of an angry populace rather
people got used to easy and entertaining
distractions engaging with difficult
ideas is by its very nature hard in the
short term it is so much more relaxing
to let ourselves be carried on a wave of
pixels and pleasure BT describes this
process in detail first books are cut
shorter then people only consume 2minute
summaries of them or two line summaries
then television shows are shortened
politics consists only of headlines and
the quality of information is fully
replaced by quantity as Bey himself says
WHL man's mind about so fast under the
pumping hands of Publishers exploiters
broadcasters and that centrifuge flings
off all unnecessary time- wasting
thought don't we give them fun that's
all we live for isn't it this is what
the philosopher bual Han would call the
acceleration of information if the state
of Fahrenheit 451s ultimate aim is to
create a compliant and docile populace
then this acceleration is the flip side
of censorship while censorship prevents
people from accessing those Oho
dangerous ideas this information
overload means that everyone is too busy
processing each new opinion statement
and fact flung at them that they
eventually just give up the world is
made totally incomprehensible and in
that confusion they will do whatever
they're told there is no way to offer up
a competing vision for the world or even
come up with a new thought the discourse
of Fahrenheit 451 consists of pure
repetition and that is exactly how Bey
thinks it should be after all no
disagreement is possible if there is no
way to come to your own opinion in the
first place we can learn a lot from this
twin strategy followed by the government
of Fahrenheit 4551 it's aim is simple
isolate people from independent thought
and then keep them fed on a diet of
inter aining empty but I think
the most important lesson is that the
people did most of this to themselves
but now I want to look into the effect
of all of this information control what
does the mind of a citizen in Farenheit
451 look like four the unexamined life
the ancient Greek philosopher Socrates
once said the unexamined life is not
worth living he spoke these words while
on trial by his own censorious
government for the crime of corrupting
the youth by exposing them to his
dangerous questioning and philosophy but
he remained steadfast in his convictions
accepting the death penalty and sticking
by his ideals but why would he be so
committed to living and spreading this
examined life I think that Farenheit 451
can help us understand the most obvious
feature of the citizens in Fahrenheit
451 is that they are almost all
completely uncritical they lose the
ability to notice anything wrong with
their situation Faber talks about this
when he says that part of the value in
all of this reading and thinking is so
we notice what might be wrong with the
world we inhabit it is telling that one
of Granger's gang of Exiles is a
professor of ethics and this makes sense
if the people only have access to one
perspective how could they even tell
what could change if they've never
leared about other civilizations other
theories and other ways of doing things
we never find out whether the elections
in Fahrenheit 451 are free and fair but
we do know that the citizens just aren't
particularly interested in the process
Mildred's friends vote for politicians
for seemingly arbitrary reasons rather
than Desiring any particular set of
policies it's similar to what Edward
Herman and Nom Chomsky call
manufacturing concept because the people
of Fahrenheit 451 only have access to
certain information they naturally come
to certain conclusions without the need
for much active government repression At
All by depriving the people of even
basic critical thought the state in
Fahrenheit 451 ensures compliance
without having to lift a finger it is
socrates's worst nightmare this also
means that on the rare occasion where
someone does get a sense that something
is wrong they can quickly be argued
against by a more informed government
agent this is clear in the debate
between BT and Montag about Midway
through the novel BT and Montag argue
about the value of books with BT saying
that they are confusing contradict one
another and cause conflict from a
reader's perspective there are thousands
of things Montag could say in response
to this he could point out that it is
through exploring contrary perspectives
that we become informed enough to come
to our own opinion he could argue that
confusion is just the pain of initial
learning he could say that conflicting
ideas may cause conflicts but the
alternative is a nagging discontent at
Living the unexamined Life ignoring
every personal and social problem in the
reflection of a screen but to do any of
this Montag would need to already have
some skill at picking apart an argument
he would need rhetoric and information
and logic but he has been purposefully
deprived of these abilities so in the
exchange it looks as if BT has won and
this could have easily caused monag to
lose confidence in his new worldview
without critical thought we are at the
mercy of a skilled sophist Montag knows
that BT's arguments are flawed but he
cannot identify why if it weren't for
this strong intuition Bey could have
easily brought him back into the fault
so far this is all in line with the
government's ultimate goal to keep
everyone thinking roughly the same thing
with only minimal variation but we also
see the severe emotional effects of
being unable to reflect or subject one's
own thoughts to scrutiny for one thing
it makes their World Views incredibly
fragile one of the reasons Mildred's
friend breaks down in tears when Montag
recites poetry is because the beauty of
the work temporarily shatters her whole
picture of the universe she has no
answer to this confrontation other than
to collapse since she has never stopped
to ask why she holds her beliefs her
Peace of Mind rests on a house of cards
blown away at the first gust of
challenge we have already touched upon
the emotional emptiness the citiz of
Fahrenheit 451 feel and this inner void
is partly caused by their inability to
stop and consider ideas it is no
coincidence that one of the works stolen
and eventually memorized by Montag is
the Book of Ecclesiastes in the Old
Testament in that book we see King
Solomon reason through his own
existential crisis and gradually resolve
it eventually with his faith in God the
particular solution doesn't matter so
much in this context rather it is the
process that Solomon goes through to rid
himself of his despair he first uses
wisdom and reason to become more aware
of life's emptiness and then to solve it
to his satisfaction in Fahrenheit 451
the inability to consider ideas to go
through Solomon's Journey leaves the
inhabitants of that world without any
solution to their emptiness it abandons
them at the mercy of a bubbling
existential dissatisfaction that pumps
away in the background without them even
noticing eventually this lack of
intellectual resources affects the very
depth of experiences that the people of
Fahrenheit 451 have access to and the
extent to which they can even understand
themselves as Lisa Felman Barett has
theorized in much of her research
language and cognitive structures form
the backdrop for how we understand our
own emotional states that is we learn to
interpret certain inner perceptions as
anger or happiness or sadness because
those are the conceptual categories we
use in the society IES we grew up in
these categorizations are not arbitrary
they are incredibly useful in fact
Barrett and her colleague Christen
linquist have inferred an interesting
implication of this Theory the more
detailed are cognitive categorizations
of our own emotional states the better
we can potentially understand how we
ourselves are feeling an example might
help to illustrate this say I only had
two words for how I was feeling either I
was feeling good or I was feeling bad
think of how much information is lost by
these Concepts I cannot consider the
energy levels of my emotional states
their relative strength or think about
their connection with my actions in any
real depth on the other hand if I have a
rich vocabulary to describe my feelings
I can have a deeper understanding of my
emotional state and with that
understanding comes control my actions
urges desires and more begin to make
sense to me the connection with books
and particularly novels is pretty
intuitive in a recent paper by Steven
Schuring and colleagues they establish a
relationship between the language used
to express emotion in fiction and
improved emotional recognition abilities
in the reader as they put it long-term
language experience and fiction reading
in particular supports emotion Concepts
through exposure to these emotions in
context if they are correct then the
intentional limiting of the conceptual
abilities of the people in Fahrenheit
451 does not just impact their ability
to understand and change the world
around them it can even make them
strange strangers to themselves their
own emotions will seem mysterious and
chaotic far beyond anything we're likely
to see around us today if Barrett is
right that there is a tight link between
the richness of our emotional Concepts
and our ability to understand our own
emotional landscape then the effective
ban on conceptual complexity enacted by
the state in Fahrenheit 451 is far more
serious than Fab suggests but this is
only the personal effect of the states
regime if we look closely we can see
even more disastrous consequences in
their overall
culture five self-obsession arrogance
and humility it is a piece of
cross-cultural philosophical wisdom that
an excessive focus on yourself can lead
to Misery we find it in the Christian
tradition in the rule of St Benedict
where humility is seen as the path to
God it occurs in many Buddhist sutus
where the guarding of the ego is
presented as bringing only despair in
the long term and the condemn of
self-obsession is a theme of modernday
positive psychology so it is notable
that the citizens in Fahrenheit 451
often exhibit an almost pathological
level of self-obsession Montag first
notes this after his initial
conversation with Clarice she takes him
completely by surprise because she seems
to be interested in him as a person
rather than simply waiting for her turn
to speak this is in stark contrast to
the other people he comes across whose
favorite topic is almost always
themselves elves and who are far more
concerned with the appearance of things
than attempting to investigate their
reality or probe into someone's inner
mind in fact we see a sort of doubling
up of self-obsession firstly people
focus on themselves far more than others
at all times and secondly they
prioritize the public image of
themselves over who they are in reality
the second of these themes is evident in
the huge disconnect between how the
characters project and the behavior they
actually exhibit the characters in the
novel profess they are happy but this is
more of a performance than a report of
their genuine emotional state when
Clarice confronts Montag by asking him
directly if he is happy Montag is lost
for words he tries to dismiss the
question it is only when he stops and
thinks that he realizes he is actually
deeply unhappy and this whole time he
had merely been putting on a front it is
this realization that begins his
transformation from State Enforcer to
literary Rebel but Montag is far from
the only one to exhibit this Behavior
one of Mildred's continual refrains
through the novel is that she and Montag
are happy and successful so why put that
all at risk with montag's new book
Obsession but this observation just
flies in the face of facts if they were
happy why did Mildred want to die why
did they not connect as people why are
they both teetering on the verge of
collapse why is Mildred's only source of
interpersonal love her parlor shows the
people of Fahrenheit 451 are in a
constant performance to convince
everyone including themselves that
everything is okay and they will use
every ounce of denial they can muster to
maintain this illusion Montag even
suggests that Captain BT must have
wanted to be killed since he gave Montag
the flamethrower and then goed him into
using it I think this theme of denial
links quite closely with the modern idea
of toxic positivity this term is used in
a variety of different ways but it
almost always involves a cultural taboo
around professing that something is not
quite right or that we are feeling
anything less than totally happy it
naturally creates a culture of
performance where regardless of how
we're actually feeling we must Express
constant positivity it almost entails
the prioritization of image over reality
and in Fahrenheit 451 the performance
has extended so far that the citizens
even perform it to themselves this
reaches its symbolic apotheosis in
Mildred mourning the loss of her
immersive TV set more than her husband's
arrest the appearance of perfect
relationships valued over the messy
business of actually connecting to a
loved one here we see the extreme
prioritization of image over reality and
self over other all in one it is the
reduction of all human life to an
aesthetic display in a shop window but
this self-obsession of the general
populace in Fahrenheit 451 is mirrored
by a more Insidious kind of Pride from
the senior agents of the state whereas
the everyday person is simply too
concerned with themselves to bother with
other people Captain Bey goes one step
further he thinks that he knows what is
best for every single other person in
the country self-concern has developed
into self- glorification B has fully
embraced a form of intellectual
arrogance that he thinks justifies his
authoritarianism what could be more
unduly overconfident than deciding that
all the people of your nation are simply
unfit to process new ideas that you know
better than any of them to such an
extent that they do not even need to
hear an alternative BT and the state
more generally imagine themselves as an
omniscient God knowing in advance what
all the best ideas will be and burning
the rest but this too does not bring the
Agents of the state happiness but only
fear and insecurity as we discussed in
the first section the attitude of the
government towards its people in
Fahrenheit 451 is abject Terror Behind
be's own display of Pride he too is
afraid alone and seemingly wishing for
an end contrasting all of this are the
fugitives and Granger what sets them
apart from the other people in
Fahrenheit 451 and the arrogance of the
state is that they value content over
presentation
and all exist to serve one another their
entire Quest relies on sharing a
communal load not one of them holds all
of their Collective knowledge but
together they have entire libraries
memorized if they are to achieve their
aim of putting it all back down on paper
in happier times then they must rely on
one another to do so secondly the very
mechanism they use is internal they care
about what is in one another's Minds
rather than the appearance of
contentment or Joy it is true that they
seem more melancholic than many of the
everyday citizens but they are not
violent towards one another nor are they
on the edge of mental implosion they
also form an important Counterpoint to
the arrogance of the state they
explicitly do not think that they are
importance instead Granger describes
them as the Guardians of the ideas in
their heads rather than imposing one set
of approved theories onto other people
they want to teach people how to think
for themselves they are not seeking
disciples or followers but independent
Minds there is no indication that the
fugitives agree with all of the books
they memorize in fact it is very
unlikely considering that many of them
will inevitably disagree but in an act
of humility they recognize that these
may be of use to others whereas Bey
doesn't trust others to think Granger
doesn't trust himself to think for
others that is the crucial difference
between these competing philosophies but
of course this is only one disagreement
between the literary fugitives and the
state another comes in their approach to
a crucial feature of humanity are
differences six an inferno of the
same right the way back in section two I
briefly mentioned the importance the
state in Fahrenheit 451 places on Unity
but it goes far beyond that the deeper
aim here is not simply to make people
United but to make them the same we have
already seen a few methods they use to
achieve this the censorship and control
of information means that people never
come to substantive disagreements this
minimization of disagreement is then
Justified on the grounds that it
prevents conflicts but there are a
number of Insidious side effects first
the world is rendered meaningless and
flat but Additionally the general public
are robbed of their individuality I've
talked about this before on the channel
but there is a pretty close relationship
between the kind of things that bring a
sense of meaning to someone's life and
the kinds of things that make a good
narrative or story in some ways this is
unsurprising what makes a good story
compelling will also make a life
compelling this is one reason why so
many images of existential hell rely on
the concept of aimless repetition kamu
has the image of Copus rolling a boulder
up a hill each day only to watch it come
crashing back down Solomon has the image
of the sun rising and setting and then
Rising again dostoevski thought that
asking someone to empty two cups of
water into one another over and over
again for no identifiable reason would
drive them mad in each case there is a
cyclical structure that defies narrative
resolution and this cycle relies on
everything staying roughly the same in
such situations there are no important
differences in the significance of
location or of time in the terminology
of Mercia eliad everything is made
profane it is all put on the same level
and as a result the extreme emphasis on
sameness also renders life featureless
in some ways the physical Banning of
books is only the physical manifestation
of a much deeper property of Fahrenheit
41's World a lack of full momentum or
broad narrative to anyone's life a
repetitive existence for each and every
citizen this sameness is clearly seen in
the routines of each character Montag
lives the same day over and over again
he gets up he burns books he goes back
home and he does the exact same thing
the next time he wakes up in the morning
this repetition is so absolute that even
ordinary or minor alterations such as
Clarice talking to Montag on his way to
or from work take him completely by
surprise Mildred spends her day simply
consuming spectacle from her television
system and talking to her friends she is
so wed to this that when her husband
tries to take a day off work for for
illness she is completely shocked she
says you've never been sick before as if
the concept of change is completely
foreign to her this complete flattening
of every moment in time to one
unimportant smudge is a recipe for
existential disaster and it heavily
contributes to this undercurrent of
Despair that we keep revisiting if hope
is the general attitude that there is
something about the future that is worth
continuing for then the world of
Fahrenheit 451 is technically hopeless
it is a Kafkaesque nightmare of
senselessness and blind repetition with
a bland smile painted on its face but
this is not the only kind of sameness
found in Fahrenheit 451 if this would be
sameness within someone's life there is
also sameness between people Montag even
comments on how all the firemen look the
same and share the same proclivities
they are all caricatures of Manliness
with black hair black brows a fiery face
and a blue steel shaved but unshaven
look Clarice remarks that in cafes
everyone says the same things and nobody
says anything different from anyone else
Mildred and her friends all vote the
same way share the same opinions and the
same routine the simple Act of talking
in the evenings is seen as dangerous and
subversive the closest thing we see in
the novel to normal
certain phrases back to one another for
instance when one of them is talking
rather nonchalantly about the prospect
of her husband possibly dying in the
upcoming War we get the following
exchange I'm not worried said Mrs Phelps
I'll let Pete do all the worrying she
giggled I'll let old Pete do all the
worrying not me I'm not worried yes said
Millie let old Pete do all the worrying
here we see both the constant repetition
of thoughts within one person Where Mrs
Phelps repeats I'm not worrying and let
Peete do all the worrying and the
repetition across people where Mildred
parrots the same phrase back to her it
is what kard might call the leveling of
humankind neither Mildred nor Mrs Phelps
is interested in being an individual
they simply want to repeat the patterns
of the other person they are each
striving to be an uncomplicated member
of what kard calls the public an
amorphous abstract idea of what everyone
thinks and for all of his newly acquired
outrage this was also exactly what
Montag was doing until about 5 minutes
ago in his first exchange with Clarice
he dutifully repeats what the fire
department has taught him even when it
is patently absurd Clarice remarks that
Montag never stops to think before
answering her questions he merely
regurgitates catchphrases from his
indoctrination and all of this is very
much in line with the plans of BT and
the state in one Illuminating passage BT
says the following we must all be alike
not everyone born free and equal as the
Constitution says but everyone made
equal each man the image of every other
then all are happy for there are no
mountains to make them cower to judge
themselves against what Bey is arguing
for here is not merely the death of the
individual but also the death of any
kind of Excellence it mirrors n's
nightmare that one day we would all be
so resentful of what another and so
deprived of our drive to create meaning
and live our own lives that we would
become crabs in buckets so afraid of our
own inadequacy that we drag others down
to our level by force in the hopes of
maintaining our everyday Pleasures he
calls people like this the last man and
thinks they represent the ultimate waste
of human potential yet in Fahrenheit 451
this is not just a side effect of BT's
actions it is the official aim behind
State policy this leveling is also very
hard to undo a vicious cycle takes over
once everyone believes the same set of
ideas and any opposing ideas are either
banned or heavily discouraged how can
people discover any other way to live
moreover as psychologists like Solomon
Ash and later Thomas Morgan and Kevin
laand have pointed out when we humans
are uncertain of something we are much
more likely to bow to social pressure
and simply conall this mirrors how the
formis in Fahrenheit 451 seemed to
happen via a Snowball Effect first
people wanted the leveling or weren't
opposed to it and then it occurred a
little and as a result the conformist
Instinct made it slightly more popular
which allowed the state to promote it
more and so on and so forth until they
arrived at their horrifying final
destination at the time the novel takes
place children spend their entire
childhood being indoctrinated by these
televisual systems a set of curated
ideas fed to them by a technology that
has a near Monopoly on information the
result is a civilization of carbon
copies living unfulfilling repetitive
lives unaware that there are even
alternative ways to exist but how did
the people of this world allow this to
happen why did no one stop them what did
the Grangers and favors of the world do
well the answer may be a sobering
shock seven compliance and in
action one of History's Eternal
questions is how large groups of
otherwise Ordinary People allow awful
things to happen when Hannah arent
recorded the trial of Adolf ikan the war
criminal responsible for countless
deaths during World War II she partly
wanted to answer this but she came to a
seemingly surprising conclusion in her
opinion ikan did not have a burning
emotional hatred of Jewish people or the
others he condemned to die she rather
saw him as a follower of other people
someone who could be filled with the
ideas around him and who was content to
Simply let horrifying things happen she
turned this along with some other
observations the banality of Evil part
of her theory was that many people would
allow unimaginable Horrors to occur so
long as it is endorsed by those around
them this hypothesis remains very
controversial some claim it was
confirmed or supported by the mgram
experiment others criticize how that
experiment was initially conducted and
they in turn have been challenged by
further mgram style experiments which
supposedly make up for the shortcomings
in the original but in Bradbury's novel
he very much comes down on the
pessimistic side of this debate the
people of Fahrenheit 451 were not by and
large intimidated into their position
they allowed it to happen and in some
cases even actively encouraged it Faber
explains that the state was only ever
able to ban books and launch this total
attack on the information landscape
because people lost interest in learning
altogether government policy and public
opinion worked in tandem people
preferred entertainment to information
so markets and the state Rose to meet
this demand and it was only later that
the situation set in permanently as
Faber himself put it I remember the
newspapers dying like huge moths no one
wanted them back no one missed them and
the government seeing how advantageous
it was circled the situation with your
fire eaters this marks another notable
difference between Fahrenheit 451 and
many other dystopias in 1984 the party
Rose to power with false promises that
were believed by the desperate citizens
of Oceania in Brave New World most
people have just been genetically
engineered to be compliant and follow
orders but in Fahrenheit 451 the people
and the eventual repressive government
were aligned in their aims they were not
lied to they just supported what the
state was doing and
perhaps more importantly there was no
real opposition fa himself States how he
and many others let go of their
principles for the sake of personal
safety and temporary security he
condemns himself and the others as
cowards who stood idly by as everything
they valued got torn away they may not
have been outright collaborators but
they all found their personal excuses to
do nothing about the unfolding situation
Faber thinks that if they had acted
early
then perhaps they could have nipped this
whole disaster in the butt but by the
time the universities and libraries
closed and the threat came to their door
it was far too late to do anything about
it all their potential allies had
already been defeated and they had no
choice but to capitulate some were
forced to go on the Run others
assimilated into this new world but they
could not save the knowledge and the
wisdom that they held so dear the French
intellectual renear was once asked what
someone ought to do with his theories
about how we persecute scapegoats to
alleviate our conscience and bolster our
societies how we might know that we've
understood this Theory and how we might
confirm it he replied that we have
reached this point when we recognize
that we too do our fair share of
persecuting and scapegoating and I think
Bradbury's story suggests a similar line
of thinking regarding our own complicity
in the world around us here it is so
easy to look down on those blindly go
along with the status quo in Fahrenheit
451 all the people who could have
resisted but did not out of either
cowardice or a blind hope that it would
never become their problem but can we
honestly look in the mirror and say that
there are not many many times when we do
the same with our principles in his work
the screw tape letters CS Lewis argues
that the first step towards evil is
convincing ourselves that matters of
morality or ideals or values are
completely divorced from The Real World
around us they are all right to think
about but not fit propositions to act
upon for Lewis as soon as this happens
we are on the path towards our
principles becoming more Theory than
reality we mouth the words of kindness
or Compassion or generosity or learning
all while remaining bitter cruel selfish
and incurious in his initial
conversations with montac Faber outlines
three conditions for his idea of a new
world world the first is access to
Quality information the second is the
time to engage with it and the third is
the freedom to act from what you've
learned he points out that books were
allowed to be banned because people no
longer wanted quality information but he
could have easily looked to his third
condition to explain the situation it is
not just that people were no longer
interested in quality information but
those who were clearly did not act based
on that information the right to act on
your own conscience is meaningless if we
sell or never do it becomes like the
freedom to have telekinetic Powers since
no one has them anyway such a right
would be completely moted dystopian
novels tend to be full of warnings part
of Orwell's Legacy in the western world
is a vigilance around the potential of
certain freedoms especially freedom of
expression to be taken away but
Bradbury's warning is subtly different
it is not simply that he wants us to be
wary of the arguments given for
censorship it goes far deeper than that
there is the more fundamental question
of whether we are living by our own
values and building a society we want to
see or whether we too are just like Fab
was having principles in theory but
never in practice even worse Have We
Become like the baguer populace so
overwhelmed with information that we
Tire of it relaxing into a warm bath of
empty entertainment instead the English
philosopher John Stuart Mill thought it
was the duty of every citizen in a state
to keep an eye on their government and
subject it to strict scrutiny this was
the lifeblood of a democratic system and
the means by which we prevent a
Devolution into tyranny this was his
answer to who watches the Watchman we do
but are we keeping up our end of the
bargain Bradbury fears we are not but
lastly I want to move from the political
back down to the personal because there
is one final victim in Fahrenheit 451
and it is not books or even specific
ideas but the very activity of deep
thought and
reflection eight the value of
reflection if there was an activity the
ancient Greek philosophers were keen on
it was contemplation Plato thought that
we could use our reflective and rational
capabilities to learn fundamental truths
about morality Beauty and more Aristotle
thought that a life of contemplation was
one of the highest goals anyone could
aspire to he said that without at least
some exercise of our rational faculties
we would not be harnessing our uniquely
human gift of detailed reflective
complex thought and there are many
instrumental reasons we might value
contemplation in his essay In Praise of
idleness Bertram Russell argues that
just as we should be wary of thought
without action an awful lot of damage is
done by action without thought as he
puts it a habit of finding pleasure in
thought rather than in action is a
safeguard against unwisdom and excessive
love of power a means of preserving
Serenity in Misfortune and peace of mind
among
worries this Echoes an argument we find
in a whole host of philosophical
traditions when the stoic philosopher
Epictetus was a slave to a brutal Master
his mind was all he had to take refuge
in likewise when boethus was condemned
to death terrified of his fate and
deprived of his freedom he turned to
contemplation to steady his mind calm
his nerves and make sense of this
abysmal situation we have already talked
about how the people of Fahrenheit 451
are robbed of access to good ideas but
so far we have mainly looked at how this
affects their capacity for critical
thought it is true that they are kept
from the skills to criticize the state
or learn new Concepts but they also lose
this Safe Haven in times of trouble for
the citizens in Fahrenheit 451 it is not
just that they have lost ownership of
their books or their ideas they have
lost control over their very Minds if we
agree with these philosophers that
contemplation is an essential skill for
weathering hardship and bearing our
situation when things go wrong then this
is a crime as great as any other that
the likes of Bey commit but it is not
just that the careful exercise of
thought can make us more resilient it
can also increase our joy the Czech
psychologist mahai shiken mahai observed
that humans are at their most fulfilled
when we are taken up with a task that
requires our entire attention seems
meaning meaningful to us and challenges
us at just the right level for him this
was not just pleasurable in the short
term but was a sustainable way of
finding long-term joy in life and the
facilitation of This Joy often came from
reflecting upon and knowing about the
object of your focus he uses the example
of listening to a long Symphony what
could be quite a dull experience if you
have no background or understanding of
Music suddenly becomes incredibly joyous
if you can give it your full attention
and identify the themes the use of
Harmony of CounterPoint and the way the
different sections play off one another
like a machine that turns human effort
into Beauty this mirrors Russell's own
thoughts where he describes how knowing
about and reflecting upon the history of
the apricot somehow makes the taste seem
sweeter the richness of the associations
actually changes his experience of the
apricot and this all takes prior mental
exertion learning and reflection and
this is to say nothing about the
potential joys of reflection itself in
his works the burnout Society the
transparency society and in focr bual
Han worries how our own social attitude
towards work and information means that
we rarely stop process our experiences
and reflect for Han this is a shame for
all the reasons we've already spoken
about but also because he views
reflection itself as potentially a great
source of pleasure it is how we turn
mere information into wisdom that is
applicable to us and it allows us to
enjoy the time spent in our heads if
blae Pascal thought that many of our
problems were caused by our inability to
sit alone in a room quietly Han thinks
that if we commit to it this time in
deep thought will become not only useful
but intrinsically pleasurable perhaps
more importantly with reflection and
thought comes Freedom not freedom in the
sense of no one putting a gun to our
heads but the freedom to make informed
decision that make sense to us if I
cannot stop think and consider then I
may make choices but these will either
be following what everyone else is doing
or simply grasping in the dark in the
vain hope that I will achieve my aims it
turns life into an incomprehensible mess
this is yet another nail in the supposed
happiness of the people in Fahrenheit
451 in Bradbury's World General respect
for the human mind has so degraded that
a reflect disposition is seen as a kind
of illness Clarice mentions she has been
placed into therapy but this is not
because she is profoundly unhappy or
because she has become violent and
erratic but simply that she displays an
unacceptable degree of thoughtfulness
the anti-intellectualism in Fahrenheit
451 has reached such a fever pitch that
thought itself is seen as a mental
disease while Mass violence and
self-destruction are simply the order of
the day it is telling that when Montag
becomes disillusioned with his work and
starts to question BT's ideology he
calls in sick and he may not even be
lying when he says this this could be
the only way he knows to describe his
condition to be at odds with the status
quo to have engaged in genuine
independent reflection this is illness
in the psychological ethical system of
Fahrenheit 451 and since it is an
illness that means that no one else has
to take that position seriously it is a
way of discrediting the clarices and
monts of the world without ever having
to confront them by definition anyone
engaged in deep thought is not
expressing a point of view they are
exhibiting a symptom people will view
the first bubblings of contemplation
like we would the first signs of a
horrible disease and will rush to get it
expunged from them as soon as possible
little do they know they are cleaving
off parts of their own Humanity in the
process this is the ultimate Evil in
Fahrenheit 451 were it not for this you
could almost believe the state's lies
that their policy prevents conflict
maintains peace and makes people happy
we could explain away the existential
malays of Montag Mildred and her friends
as only emerging when they are
confronted with an alternative Viewpoint
Bey might say it is not that they are
not thinking enough but they are still
thinking too much but from what we know
about the effects of reflection and
thought how it can help us to withstand
harm to multiply our Joys and Achieve
Freedom this position is no longer
tenable even if we take the authorities
at their word and ignore the violence
the Despair and the repression we would
still be left with millions of people
purposefully robbed of one of the
fundamental pillars of a human life
without the ability to direct their own
minds to think and to reflect these
people may have been saved from the
acute pain of conflict but they are
Damned to a dull Hell worst of all they
have had something that is fundamentally
and unalienable theirs stolen from them
the subtlety of Bradbury's dystopia is
that even if Bey was correct in all of
his claims if we look more closely we
still see it would hardly be worth it
and I will leave you with one final
quote from Bradbury's afterward to the
50th anniversary of his book you don't
have to B books do you if the world
starts to fill up with non-readers
non-learners who after a while will know
or Care thank you so much for watching
and have a wonderful day and if you want
to watch some of my other longer videos
I have a playlist of them right here